你好黑客
hello hackers
欢迎回到pwn学院
welcome back to pwn College
这是面向返回编程模块的第四个视频
this is the fourth video in the return oriented programming module
我们将讨论ROPing时会遇到的问题
we're going to be talking about complications you run into when ROPing
好吧
all right
我要介绍一些问题
I'm just going to go through a bunch of issues
谈谈影响
talk about how this impact you and
以及如何绕过这些问题
how you might bypass these issues
问题一，有限的栈控制
issue No. 1 limited stack control
有时候你能溢出的范围是相当少的
right sometimes your amount that you can overflow is actually fairly low
也许你只能溢出返回地址
maybe you can just overflow the return address
这就是你能控制的全部
and that's all you get
这种情况经常发生
this happens a lot
有几种方法可以处理
there are several ways to deal with it
一种处理方法是
one way to deal with it is
我先理一下
let me actually go through that alright
为什么会出现这种情况
so why might this occur
一个原因是
one reason it could occur is that
有些漏洞只能溢出有限的范围
there're still limited overflow
假设在一个每元素8字节的数组中有一个off by one漏洞
off by one that lets you in let's say an array of eight byte elements
只能让你重写返回地址
that let's you overwrite just the return address
或
or
你无法输入空字节
maybe you can't input any null bytes
当你要输入amd64中地址的最高有效位时
when you input  the most significant bytes of an address on amd64
它们大部分都是00
they're null for the most part
那你的溢出将被00截断
then your overflow ends
这样你就只能触发一个gadget
and then you can only trigger one gadget right
事实证明你只用一个gadget就能成功
turns out you can win with just one gadget and
有几种方法可以做到这一点
there are several ways to do it
一种方法是触发所谓的神奇gadget
one way is to trigger what is called a magic gadget
当你调用system库函数时
when you call the system library call
设置好execve的参数
you set up a call to execve
/bin/sh -c和想让系统执行的命令
/bin/sh -c and whatever command you set to system
如果你很幸运，跳到了system中
if you are lucky and you jump part way into system
你可以触发execve /bin/sh
you could trigger execve /bin/sh right
这实际上能行，这个就叫神奇gadget
and it actually works this called the magic gadget
有工具
there are tools
其中一个在我的CTF工具库中
one of them is on my CTF tools repository
它会帮你找到这些gadget的地址
that will find the address of these gadgets for you
问题是这些gadget
the problem is that these gadgets
对执行环境有要求
have requirements on how the the stage should look like
RAX、RSI或RDI需要是特定值
what RAX or RSI or RDI need to be
例如，RDX可能需要为空
for example RDX might need to be null
那么这个env可以传入一个null
so that this environment can be passed in as null
然后
and then you know
这个system调用将成功
the execve system will succeed
这并不总是那么简单
so it's not always super simple
有时
and sometimes
尝试跳到system的不同偏移
it's easier to just try jumping into every different offset of system on your machine and libc
看看会发生什么更容易
and see what happens
例如，你可以执行一些随机的事情
for example you might be able to execute some random thing
它只是执行一些文件
that just execve some file
然后你可以在那个文件里放一些东西
and then you can put something in that file
你在shellcoding模块中完成了此操作
you've done this again in the shellcoding module
你在那里只能给execve传一个字符
where you were able to execve 1 letter
创建一个名字只有一个字母的程序
but of course by creating a program with that one letter name
你就能够执行它
you were able to execute it
这是一个值得思考的例子
just an example to think about
就神奇gadget而言
in terms of a magic gadget
当然，神奇gadget通常都是必备之物
of course the magic gadget is often the go to thing
因为想获得shell，想调用system
because people want a shell people want to run system right
想获得flag
you want the flag
您不一定非得运行system
you don't necessarily need to run system
chown就够用
chown is great for you
还有很多其他的东西
and a whole lot of other things right
事实上，system是不好的
in fact system is bad
因为默认情况下bin sh会丢掉特权
because bin sh will drop privileges by default
所以你需要的是
so what you want to do is
找到一个适合你的神奇gadget
find a magic gadget that works for you
例如，这个神奇gadget可能是chown库函数的一部分
that magic gadget might be part way into the chown library call for example
好的，问题2
all right issue 2
地址空间布局随机化
address space layout randomization
这实际上也与问题1有关
this actually has to do also with issue 1
你也只能触发一个gadget
where you can only do one gadget
我会讲为什么
I'll talk about why
如果你不知道内存中各部分的位置
if you don't know where anything is in memory
你就无法写出有用的返回地址链
you can't write intelligent return addresses
这是行不通的
it just won't work
对，其实你们已经遇到过这个问题了
right but you've already seen this problem
你在babymem中遇到过
you've seen this in babymem
你通过覆盖部分返回地址解决了这个问题
and you solved it with a partial return pointer overwrite
在这里也能这样做
and you can do the same thing here
你可以只覆盖返回地址的最低几位
you can override just the lowest bits of the return address
或者最低的两个字节
or the lowest two bytes
成功的几率是1/16
you have a 1 and 16 chance of surviving that
当程序返回时
or the program does when it returns
你可以重写它指向某个有趣的地方
and you can override it to point somewhere interesting
通常想做的是
often what you want to do
覆盖返回地址让它跳回开头
is override it to loop the program back to the beginning
也许稍微修改了进程环境
maybe with a slightly corrupted state
这样
so that
当它执行了某些行动
when it takes certain actions
之后，进程状态会被修改的越来越多
later on it'll start corrupting more and more and more
循环程序类似于babymem中的重复后门
looping a program is similar to the repeat backdoor in babymem
当时你用它来获取软件信息
that you used to retrieve information about the software
只要你能让这个程序保持运行
as long as you can keep the program alive
让它做你想做的事的几率就不为零
your chance that you can get it to do what you wanted to do stay non zero
好的，循环程序的次数越多
alright the longer you can loop the program
循环一遍又一遍
loop it again loop it again
一点一点地泄露信息
try to leak information little by little
你的胜算就越大
the better odds you are
另一个
the other
这是处理ASLR的一种方法
so that's one way of of kind of starting to deal with ASLR
顺便说一下，如果你是从main返回
if by the way you are returning from main
返回地址指向libc中的libc_start_main里
so the return address is into libc_start_main which is in libc
覆盖部分返回地址
with a partial return point overwrite
你也许能命中一个神奇gadget
you might be able to hit a magic gadget
它会帮你做你想做的事
that will do what you wanted to do for you
另一种绕过ASLR的方法是
the other way of course to work around the ASLR is
泄露地址空间
a disclosure address space
或者说
or
利用信息泄露漏洞
an information disclosure
把地址泄露给你
that will leak out an address to you
但这是非常看情况的
but that's very situational
不是通用的
not as as general
当然，方法一也不是那么通用
of course workround one isn't so general either
方法1这种循环程序的想法也适用于有限栈控制
workaround 1 this idea of looping the program also works for a limited stack right
另一个适用于有限栈控制的方法
the other thing that works for a limited stack right
我们在上个视频中讨论过
that we talked about in the last video
是栈pivot
is a stack pivot
你只用一个gadget
you use your single gadget
如果你只能找到一个gadget来旋转栈
if you only had to get one gadget to pivot the stack to
例如交换RSP和RAX
for example exchange RSP and RAX
并且RAX可能指向你有更多控制的输入缓冲区
and RAX might point to an input buffer that you control more of
另一种方法是
another thing you could do
不从头开始循环
is loop the program not quite to the beginning
而从read函数调用准备开始
but to the setup of the read function call
但现在
but now
因为你修改了某些进程状态
because you've corrupted some part of the state
让它读取的量更大
the amount that it reads is bigger
然后你可以读取更大的ROP链
and then you can read in a larger ROP chain
然后实施你的攻击
and carry out your attack
好吧，无论如何，ASLR是个问题
okay anyways ASLR is a problem
这些小方法可以让你尝试绕过
there are these little ways that you can kind of still survive with it
但实际上，这并不好用
but realistically it is not good
你可能需要某种程度上的内存泄露来绕过它
and you'll likely need a memory disclosure somehow to get by it
下一个问题是栈金丝雀
next issue stack canaries
这些对ROP来说是残酷的
these are brutal against ROP
ROP需要覆盖返回地址
ROP requires a return pointer overwrite
这通常会覆盖栈金丝雀
which often requires an overwriting of the stack canary
你得想个办法绕过它
you'll need to figure out a way to bypass it
和在babymem中的做法类似
similar to how you did in babymem
是的，没有一劳永逸的办法（银弹）
right there's no silver bullet
栈金丝雀非常有效
stack canaries are extremely effective
记住这些
just keep those in mind
还有一些有趣少见的学术解决方案
there are also interesting exotic academic solutions
用于尝试防御ROP
that have been attempted to solve ROP
使ROP不那么强大
to make ROP less powerful
这些解决方案有
these solutions range from
去除ROP gadget
removing ROP gadgets
确保函数中没有
so you know making sure that functions don't have
pop RDI; RET之类的
pop RDI; RET
但是那些真的很繁重
right but those are really onerous
除了学术论文之外，我从未见过它们被实际应用
I've never seen them actually deployed outside of academic papers
即使是学术论文也无法消除所有ROP gadget
and even the academic papers don't eliminate all ROP gadgets
实际上你不需要那么多ROP gadget
and you don't actually need that many ROP gadgets
来成功实施攻击
to carry out these successful attack
可以尝试检测何时发生ROP攻击
you can try to detect when a ROP attack is happening
你说，好吧，没关系，我们会被ROP攻击
you say okay that's fine we'll have a ROP attack
但是当系统调用发生时
but when a syscall occurs
就检查一下栈
you'll go through the stack
看看它是什么样子
and see what what it looks like
是否看起来像ROP攻击
if it looks like a ROP attack
或者你会记日志
or you will keep a log
查看处理器指令日志
you look at the processor instruction log
看看在最后一百条指令中执行了多少ret
and see how many RETs were executed in the last hundred instructions
你会说，这看起来像ROP
and you say okay this looks like ROP
然后终止程序
and then kill the program
这实际上在Windows中得到了应用
this is actually deployed in practice in Windows
例如，Windows为保护自己免受ROP
for example Windows protects itself against ROP
使用了KBouncer技术
using this KBouncer technique
它被应用了，但是可以绕过
it's used but it's bypassable right
如果你控制了足够的程序用来ROP
if you have enough controlled program to be comfortably ropping
然后你就可以隐身了
then you can likely stealth yourself
你可以创建一个ROP链
you can create a ROP chain
并且掩盖它是ROP链的事实
that tries to hide the fact that it's a ROP chain
比如，通过运行其他良性代码等等
by running other benign code etc etc
对吧
right and
最终使系统误以为ROP没有发生
in the end fools the system into thinking that ROP isn't happening
还有一类学术解决方案叫做
and then there's this category of academic solutions called
控制流完整性
control flow integrity
控制流完整性是在十多年前提出的
control flow integrity was proposed over a decade ago now
一群研究人员
by a bunch of researchers
他们中的许多人仍然活跃在这个领域
many of whom are still active in the field
在一篇名为《控制流完整性》的论文中
in a paper called Control Flow Integrity
它的核心思想是
the core idea is that
对于任何间接跳转，任何返回
for any indirect jump any return
任何以寄存器作为参数的调用
any call that takes a register as an argument
任何攻击者可以控制的间接跳跃
an indirect jump  something that an attacker could control
我们输入一些代码
we put in some code
确保在运行时跳转的目标是预计的
to make sure that the target of that jump at run time is what it's supposed to be
当然很难知道目标都是什么
of course you don't know the target
在运行时很难知道所有目标应该是什么
it's hard to know at run time what all the targets are supposed to be
代码非常复杂
code is very complex
但可以尽力而为
but you do your best
这催生了一场技术军备竞赛
and this spawned a whole arms race of techniques that
一方防御ROP
try to prevent ROP
一方绕过ROP防御
and techniques that try to bypass techniques that try to prevent ROP
那是一段疯狂的时光
it was a wild time
大概在2015 - 2016年左右
this is around 2015 2016
那时每一篇学术论文的主题
it is every other academic paper coming out with about
不是防止ROP
either preventing ROP
就是ROP防御绕过
or preventing the prevention of ROP
太疯狂了，然后我们有了很多技巧
it was insane and we had tons of techniques
我们有面向块的编程，这是可以的
we had block oriented programming and this is okay
还可以进行ROP但是是以代码块为单位
we can ROP but on a block level
非常高层的指令
like on a very high level of instructions
有点像我们在一开始的介绍中的例子
kind of like what we did in our example intro in the beginning
用程序的这些大块
say okay you take these huge chunks of the program
通过精心设计状态和状态间的过渡
and by carefully crafting the state and transition between them
而不是用小gadget
instead of little gadgets
我们可以用这些程序的大块来构建攻击
we can build our attack out of large parts of the program
来绕过某些技术
to bypass certain techniques
事实上
in fact
这些程序块甚至可以以
these large parts of the program could even start on
间接控制流转移的合法目标开始
valid targets for indirect control flow transfers
还有面向跳转编程
there was jump oriented programming
只是不再用RET了
says we just don't use returns right
我们使用跳转指令代替RET
we use indirect jumps instead
这样能绕过KBounce或RoPecker之类的东西
this bypass of stuff like KBounce or RoPecker and so forth
这些系统层面
these sort of system level
允许ROP，但会检测对系统调用的调用
let people ROP but then detect when they try to make syscalls
还有面向call编程、面向sigreturn编程等
there's call oriented program sigreturn
出现了各种疯狂的ROP变体
all sorts of you know crazy ROP variants that have come up
面向数据编程, 很酷
data oriented program is kind of cool
它表示
it says alright
不劫持控制流
instead of hijacking any control flow at all
我们来修改程序数据吧
let's just carefully corrupt the program's data
这样我们就可以控制程序了
so that we can pop it the program
当然，这取决于程序是做什么的
of course this depends on what the program does and
不管你能不能做到
whether you can do that or not
但是你可以想象
but you can imagine that
如果你攻击的程序是
if the program you're attacking is
Bash或 /bin/sh
bash or bin you know /bin/sh
通过修改它的数据
then by corrupting its data
你可以让它做任何你想做的事
you can get it to do anything you want on your behalf
因为它是一个命令处理器
because it is a command processor
处理数据，执行命令
process that data and that execute that commands
好了，控制流完整性最近变成了现实
all right control flow integrity was recently made an actual reality
到目前为止，所有这些学术技术
up until now all of these academic techniques
支持控制流完整性的
for control flow integrity
反对控制流完整性的
against control flow integrity
大部分都没有真正被使用
for the most part were not really used
有时它们会被部署在Windows系统中
sometimes they'd be deployed in Windows
但是还能绕的过
but by passable and so forth
最近，我是说非常近，2020年9月
recently and I mean very recently September 2020
英特尔发布了一系列新的处理器
Intel released a series of new processors
支持CET即控制流强制技术
that has CET Control flow Enforcement Technology
这是什么意思?
what does this mean
用我们熟悉的话讲
it means in terms of relevance for us
CET增加了endbr64指令
CET adds the endbr64 instruction
这可能看起来很熟悉
this likely sounds familiar to you
如果你objdump过最近编译的二进制文件
if you objdump any recently compiled binary
比如？？？
for example on the boons 2004
在每个函数的开头都有这个endbr指令
at the beginning of every function is this endbr instruction
endbr告诉处理器
endbr tells the processor
任何启用了CET的处理器
any processor enabled that has CET enabled
告诉处理器嘿
tells that processor hey
这是间接控制流切换的合法目标
this is a valid target of an Indirect control flow transfer
处理器确保当Ret时
and the processor make sure that when you do a Ret
你执行的下一条指令是endbr
the next instruction you execute is endbr
否则它将终止程序
otherwise it kills the program
没启用CET的处理器就什么也不做
processors without CET those instructions simply do nothing
就和nop一样
they're literally a nop
所以
and so
这会让ROP更难实现
what this does is make ROP a lot harder
你不能再
you can no longer
一旦这些处理器被广泛采用
you know as soon as these processors become widely adopted
你再也不能把这些gadget连在一起了
you'll no longer be able to chain these little gadgets together
你必须串联各个函数
you'll really have to chain whole functions
或者函数的片段了
or pieces of functions
它们是这些控制流切换的合法目标
that are valid targets for these control flow transfers
这将会很棘手
it's gonna be tricky
它不能彻底防止ROP
it won't block ROP
仍然有一些高级技术可以使用
there's still advanced techniques
比如面向块的编程，这还是可行的
like block oriented programming that will be viable
但这会使他们的开发变得更加复杂
but it'll complicate their exploitation quite a lot
事实上
in fact
可能这几年需要完全重做这个模块
I'll probably have to completely redo this module within a couple years
随着这些处理器的普及
as these processors become common place
或者至少增加模块内容
or at least augment the module
这将是非常有趣的
it'll be very interesting to see
好吧
all right
最后的终极挑战
the final ultimate challenge
如果你什么都没有怎么办
what if you don't have anything
你不知道东西在哪里
you don't know where things are
ASLR开启了
ASLR is on
你甚至不知道你正在利用的是什么程序
but you also don't even know what the program is that you are exploiting right
事实证明，你能做到盲打
turns out you can hack completely blind
而且你们已经做过了
and you have done much of this right
就像你做babymem题时熟悉的
the intuition as you well know from babymem
只有在程序开始时才随机化
that things are only randomized at program start
在内存错误模块
in the memory error module
在最后一关
in the final level
你一点一点地破解了程序
you broke a program piece by piece
因为它每次处理请求都会fork子进程
because it kept forking at every request
这样程序会启动
so the program would start up
会fork一个请求处理进程
it would fork off a request handler
你将和它互动
and you would interact with it
然后你溢出金丝雀
you would overflow the canary
你用1溢出金丝雀，程序崩溃
and you would overflow it with one and it crash
你用2溢出它，程序崩溃
you overflowed it with two and it would crash
最终你会得到正确的第一个字节
eventually you would get that first byte correct
程序不会崩溃，然后你开始暴破第二个字节
it won't crash and then you go onto the second byte
你可以暴力破解出金丝雀值
you can brute force the canary
返回地址甚至整个栈
the return address and the entire stack
一个字节一个字节地泄漏出所有控制流的相关信息
byte by byte to leak out all control flow relevant information
你在babymem中做过
you did that in babymem
在babyrev的最后一关，如果你还记得
and then in babyrev if you remember the last level
你对一个随机的Yan85指令集进行了盲攻击
you did a blind attack against a randomized Yan85 instruction set
你不了解这些指令
that you didn't have the mapping for
你通过发送一些输入来实现
and you did that by sending some input
等待一个响应信号
and waiting for a survival signal
解读这个信号，然后说好
interpreting that signal and saying okay
我发出的一定是即时指令
what I sent must have been an immediate instruction
你可以在这个奇怪的ROP机器上做同样的事情
you can do the same thing on this weird machine of ROP
所以一旦你一个字节一个字节地泄露出ASLR
right so once you byte by byte leak out ASLR
或者栈金丝雀值，任何你需要的
or the stack canaries everything that you need
然后你就可以开始
then you can start
尝试对奇怪机进行分析
doing this crazy weird machine introspection of blindly leaking out
使用泄露Yan85的相同方法
in the same way that you leaked out Yan85
一种理解程序各部分功能的方法
a way to understand what part of the program do what
你要做的是找到一个合适的系统调用
all you really need to do is find a right system call
或者一些合适的函数
or some right functionality
他们能让你泄露出程序
that will then let you leak out the program
然后让你们解出来
and then let you solve it
这种技术被称为盲ROP
this technique is called Blind ROP
它于2014年由Andrea Bittau提出
it was published by Andrea Bittau in 2014
不幸的是安德烈
unfortunately Andrea
在过去的几年里
in the last couple of years
死于一场摩托车事故
died in a motorcycle accident
但他创造的技术是不可思议的
but the technique that he created was incredible and
他的演讲很精彩
the talk was amazing
我不确定是否有记录
I'm not sure if it's recorded somewhere
但真的很酷
but it was really cool
他在台上运行的是最新版本打好补丁的Apache
he on stage you know ran a fully patched up to date version of Apache
或者Nginx，我不记得具体是什么web服务器了
or Nginx I don't remember some web server
除了一个控制流的漏洞
except for with one vulnerability which with a control flow
一个允许劫持控制流的栈溢出漏洞
a stack overflow that allowed control flow hijacking
然后他使用盲ROP泄漏出了不光是ASLR
and then he used blind ROP to leak out not just ASLR
还有金丝雀，还有整个二进制程序
and the canary but also the whole binary
然后利用它
and then exploited it
这是非常酷的
it was very cool to see
非常酷的演讲
a very cool presentation
嗯
um
好了，这些是一些复杂的问题
alright so those are some complications
可以说是可能遇到的非常困难的问题
like very difficult complications you might run into um
在你的ROP探险过程中
when you are on your roping adventures
希望
hopefully
这让你具备了对付他们的能力。祝你好运
this has equipped you to deal with them good luck